Michael K. Mabey



(480) 788–3411 ♦ mmabey@ieee.org Ø ♦ mikemabey.com Ø github.com/mmabey Ø ♦ 🗑 bitbucket.org/mmabey Ø

EDUCATION

Ph.D. Computer Science - Information Assurance

Dec 2017

Arizona State University

Tempe, AZ

Committee: Gail-Joon Ahn (Co-Chair), Adam Doupé (Co-Chair), Stephen S. Yau, Jooyung Lee, Ziming Zhao

Dissertation: Forensic Methods and Tools for Web Environments

The Web is one of the most exciting and dynamic areas of development in today's technology. However, web environments also present a set of new challenges for digital forensic examiners, making their jobs even more difficult. In my dissertation, I present (1) a framework for web environment forensics, which gives examiners a method for how to approach web-based evidence; (2) a method to identify extensions installed on encrypted web thin clients without breaking the encryption; and (3) an approach to reconstructing the timeline of events on encrypted web thin clients by using service provider APIs as a proxy for directly analyzing the device. I also introduce several structured formats that I customized to accommodate the unique features of web-based evidence while also facilitating tool interoperability and information sharing.

M.S. Computer Science — Information Assurance

Aug 2011

Arizona State University

Tempe, AZ

Committee: Gail-Joon Ahn (Chair), Stephen S. Yau, Dijiang Huang

Thesis: Collaborative Digital Forensics: Architecture, Mechanisms, and Case Study &

B.S. Computer Science - Information Systems

May 2009

Utah State University

Logan, UT

Jun 2013 - Aug 2013, Jun 2014 - Aug 2014

Fort Meade, MD

EXPERIENCE SUMMARY

Student Trainee (Civilian)

US Army

Dec 2017 – Present
Phoenix, AZ
Nov 2009 – Dec 2017
Tempe, AZ
May 2016 – Aug 2016
Phoenix, AZ
Aug 2010 – Dec 2015
Tempe, AZ
Sep 2015 – Oct 2015
Chandler, AZ
Jul 2015 – Sep 2015
Phoenix, AZ
Aug 2011 – Dec 2014
Tempe, AZ

Graduate Student Summer InternMay 2011 – Jul 2011Sandia National LaboratoriesAlbuquerque, NMGraduate Student Recruitment Specialist/WebmasterJul 2006 – Aug 2009Electrical & Computer Engineering Department, USULogan, UT

Technician AidSep 2006 – Aug 2009

Electrical & Computer Engineering Department, USU Logan, UT

Store Attendant Jun 2005 – Sep 2008

Electrical & Computer Engineering Department, USU Logan, UT

Lab TechnicianKWM Electronics Co.
West Jordan, UT

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Computer Scientist (Civilian)

Dec 2017 - Present

US Army, NETCOM, Data Science Directorate

Phoenix, AZ

Grade: GS-0854-11 Step 1

Service: Competitive Tenure: Conditional, Full-Time

· Interfaced with ASU faculty to collaborate on data analytic capabilities for monitoring the DoD Information Network (DoDIN) and conducting defensive cyber operations (DCO).

Civilian Reserve/Intern

May 2016 - Aug 2016

Arizona Department of Public Safety

Phoenix, AZ

· Updated the content, layout, and topics of the security policy for the Arizona Counter Terrorism Information Center (ACTIC) for clarity and to be in compliance with recommendations from the Department of Homeland Security. Created training slides to accompany the new security policy.

 Summer Intern
 Jul 2015 – Sep 2015

Arizona Cyber Threat Response Alliance (ACTRA)

Phoenix, AZ

· Designed an operationalized workflow for Arizona Infragard member organizations to share **threat intelligence** through a common **STIX/TAXII** platform.

Student Trainee (Civilian)

Jun 2013 - Aug 2013, Jun 2014 - Aug 2014

US Army

Fort Meade, MD

Grade: GG-0199-09 Step 1 Service

Service: Excepted Tenure: Permanent, Full-Time

· Summer internships in connection with DoD IASP scholarship.

Graduate Student Summer Intern

May 2011 - Jul 2011

Sandia National Laboratories

Albuquerque, NM

- · Helped design a dynamic malware analysis framework built on **OpenStack**, allowing incident responders to define customizable analysis environments and use arbitrary analysis tools for triage or manual analysis.
- · Wrote **Python** scripts to automate the setup process for using a SheevaPlug computer as a wireless intrusion detection agent running **Kismet**.

Graduate Student Recruitment Specialist/Webmaster

Jul 2006 – Aug 2009

Electrical & Computer Engineering Department, USU

Logan, UT

- · Primary responsibilities included maintaining and augmenting the department website using PHP, MySQL, and other basic web technologies like CSS, JavaScript, and an SMTP server.
- · Completed multiple graphic design projects for the department using **GIMP**, **Adobe Photoshop**, and **Adobe Illustrator**.

- · Replaced a **MS Access** database by porting the old data to a **MySQL** server and creating a set of **Python** programs with the **Dabo** framework that interfaced with the database.
- · Created a testing environment using an Apache web server, PHP, MySQL, and SVN.
- · Gathered statistics on web visitors, inquiries from students, and applicants' credentials for the purpose of improving the department's graduate student recruitment processes.
- · Responded to inquiries from potential domestic and international graduate students.

Technician Aid Sep 2006 – Aug 2009

Electrical & Computer Engineering Department, USU

Logan, UT

- · Built and maintained computers for department faculty and student labs.
- · Installed and configured various software on Windows machines for faculty, staff, and students.
- Created and restored backup images of lab computers using Norton Ghost and Acronis Truelmage.
- · Protected lab computers using Faronics Deep Freeze.

Store Attendant Jun 2005 – Sep 2008

Electrical & Computer Engineering Department, USU

Logan, UT

- · Maintained equipment and instruments in the labs for electrical engineering students.
- Performed store duties including maintaining inventory, serving customers, cleaning rooms, and running errands.

Lab TechnicianKWM Electronics Co.
West Jordan, UT

- · Worked closely with CEO/Head Engineer to build prototypes of electronic devices.
- · Used various soldering techniques on both through-hole and surface-mount parts.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Research Assistant Nov 2009 – Dec 2017

Security Engineering for Future Computing (SEFCOM) Lab &, ASU

Tempe, AZ

Lab Directors: Gail-Joon Ahn, Adam Doupé, Ziming Zhao, Yan Shoshitaishvili

- · Projects:
 - Designed a framework for conducting forensics on web environments that addresses the unique challenges forensic examiners face in this domain.

Publications: [S1]

- Implemented a forensic tool in **Python** that uses the G Suite APIs as a proxy for analyzing encrypted **Chromebooks** to reconstruct the timeline of events of an incident.
- Created a method for identifying extensions installed on Chrome OS by analyzing the encrypted files on the hard drive. Wrote an accompanying crawler in Python (and using Ansible, Celery, MySQL, sshfs, and OpenStack) to download all extensions on the Chrome Web Store and analyze them. Publications: [J1, P2, BL2, BL3]
- Helped design and implement a cloud-based version of the International Capture the Flag (iCTF) competition, allowing educators to more easily host their own CTF competitions. Used Ansible,
 Vagrant, Amazon EC2, and Python for the implementation and deployment.

Publications: [C1]

- Developed a forensic acquisition approach for web email that reestablishes persistent cookie sessions stored by a browser, and automated the process using **Python** and **Selenium**.
 Publications: [C2]
- Designed and implemented the core components of a modular, highly scalable, collaboration-centric
 digital forensic framework built on the **OpenStack** cloud architecture. Functions of the components
 included distributed job scheduling, storage management, and concise evidence representation and
 transmission.

Publications: [C4, BC1, P4]

- · Other experience:
 - Maintained fifteen servers for the lab, including a public-facing router, an OpenVPN server, a reverseproxy web server with TLS certificate management, an OpenStack cloud, switches transmitting VLAN-tagged traffic, and a GitLab server.
- · Sponsors:
 - Department of Defense Information Assurance Scholarship Program (IASP)
- Department of Energy
- National Science Foundation

RESEARCH INTERESTS

- · Digital Forensics
 - Web and Email Forensics
 - Evidence Representation Formats
 - Forensics on Non-Traditional Devices
- · Cyber Security
 - Threat Intelligence Sharing
 - Web Security

TECHNICAL STRENGTHS & QUALIFICATIONS

Programming Languages

Forensic Tools
Protocols & APIs

Network Administration/Security

Operating Systems

Cloud Architectures

Databases

Python, Bash, C/C++, HTML, CSS, LEX FTK, Sleuth Kit & Autopsy, dd, HxD, etc. JSON, XML, AMQP, REST, STIX, RabbitMQ Ansible, OpenVPN, ufw, lighttpd, Caddy, Wireshark

Windows, & Linux, O Chrome OS

vviildows, & Liliux, & Ci

OpenStack, Amazon EC2

MySQL, SQLite

PUBLICATIONS

Peer-Reviewed Conference Proceedings

- [C1] Erik Trickel, Francesco Disperati, Eric Gustafson, Faezeh Kalantari, Mike Mabey, Naveen Tiwari, Yeganeh Safaei, Adam Doupé, and Giovanni Vigna. "Shell We Play A Game? CTF-as-a-service for Security Education". In: 2017 USENIX Workshop on Advances in Security Education (ASE 17). USENIX Association, August 2017.
- [C2] Justin Paglierani, **Mike Mabey**, and Gail-Joon Ahn. "Towards Comprehensive and Collaborative Forensics on Email Evidence". In: *Collaborative Computing: Networking, Applications and Worksharing (Collaboratecom), 2013 9th International Conference Conference on.* October 2013, pp. 11–20. DOI: 10.4108/icst.collaboratecom.2013.254125 ...
- [C3] Wonkyu Han, **Mike Mabey**, and Gail-Joon Ahn. "Simulation-based validation for smart grid environments". In: 2013 IEEE 14th International Conference on Information Reuse & Integration (IRI). IEEE, August 2013, pp. 14−21. ISBN: 978-1-4799-1050-2. DOI: 10.1109/IRI.2013.6642448 ☑.
- [C4] **Mike Mabey** and Gail-Joon Ahn. "Towards Collaborative Forensics: Preliminary Framework". In: *Information Reuse and Integration (IRI), 2011 IEEE International Conference on.* August 2011, pp. 94–99. DOI: 10.1109/IRI.2011.6009527 ☑.

Peer-Reviewed Journal Papers

[J1] **Mike Mabey**, Adam Doupé, Ziming Zhao, and Gail-Joon Ahn. "dbling: Identifying extensions installed on encrypted web thin clients". In: *Digital Investigation* 18 (August 2016). The Proceedings of the Sixteenth Annual DFRWS Conference, S55–S65. ISSN: 17422876. DOI: 10.1016/j.diin.2016.04. 007 \(\mathref{c}. \)

[J2] Wonkyu Han, **Mike Mabey**, Gail-Joon Ahn, and Tae Sung Kim. "Simulation-Based Validation for Smart Grid Environments: Framework and Experimental Results". In: *Integration of Reusable Systems*. Ed. by Thouraya Bouabana-Tebibel and Stuart H Rubin. Vol. 263. Advances in Intelligent Systems and Computing. (Extended version of [C3]). Springer International Publishing, February 2014, pp. 27–44. ISBN: 978-3-319-04716-4. DOI: 10.1007/978-3-319-04717-1_2 ☑.

Peer-Reviewed Book Chapters

[BC1] Mike Mabey and Gail-Joon Ahn. "Towards Collaborative Forensics". In: *Information Reuse and Integration in Academia and Industry*. Ed. by Tansel Özyer, Keivan Kianmehr, Mehmet Tan, and Jia Zeng. (Extended version of [C4]). Springer Vienna, 2013, pp. 237–260. ISBN: 978-3-7091-1537-4. DOI: 10.1007/978-3-7091-1538-1_12 ☑.

Invited Talks

[T1] **Mike Mabey**. "dbling: Identifying Extensions Installed on Encrypted Web Thin Clients". Presentation given at the Sixteenth Annual DFRWS Conference on paper [J1]. August 2016.

Poster Presentations

- [P1] Erik Trickel, Faezeh Kalantari, Yeganeh Safaei, Lakshmi Srinivas, Naveen Tiwari, **Mike Mabey**, Sukwha Kyung, and Wonkyu Han. *Capture the Flag in the Cloud. Symposium on Information Assurance Research and Education, ASU*. October 2016.
- [P2] **Mike Mabey**, Jeremy Whitaker, Gail-Joon Ahn, and Adam Doupé. *Towards Forensics for Web Thin Clients. Symposium on Information Assurance Research and Education, ASU*. November 2015.
- [P3] Jeremy Whitaker, **Mike Mabey**, Gail-Joon Ahn, and Adam Doupé. *Forensic Analysis on Mobile Devices.* Symposium on Information Assurance Research and Education, ASU. October 2014.
- [P4] **Mike Mabey**, Justin Paglierani, and Gail-Joon Ahn. *Towards Collaborative Forensics. Workshop on Information Assurance Research and Education, ASU*. April 2012.
- [P5] James Bridges, Kasimir Gabert, and **Michael Mabey**. *Cyber Tracer*. *University Day, Sandia National Laboratories*. July 2011.

Works Submitted (In Press)

[S1] Mike Mabey, Adam Doupé, Ziming Zhao, and Gail-Joon Ahn. "Challenges, Opportunities, and a Framework for Web Environment Forensics". In: Advances in Digital Forensics XIV: 14th IFIP WG 11.9 International Conference, New Delhi, January 3-5, 2018, Revised Selected Papers. (In press). 2018.

HONORS AND AWARDS

DoD Information Assurance Scholarship Program (IASP) Recipient (5 years)
 Inducted into Eta Kappa Nu (HKN) Engineering Honors Society

2012 – 2017
Nov 2010

· Eagle Scout, Boy Scouts of America 2002

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Invited Lectures

Lecture Title: "Digital Forensics and the Internet of Things"
 Class: CSE 469 Computer and Network Forensics, Arizona State University Invited by: Dr. Ziming Zhao
 Lecture Title: "IoT Security"

Class: CSE 465 Information Assurance, Arizona State University

· Lecture Title: "Introduction to Cryptography"

Invited by: Dr. Stephen S. Yau Sep 2016

Class: CSE 465 Information Assurance, Arizona State University Invited by: Dr. Stephen S. Yau

Teaching Assistant

Aug 2010 - Dec 2015

Arizona State University

• CSE 465 Information Assurance with Dr. Gail-Joon Ahn: Fall 2010, Fall 2015.

· CSE 469 Computer and Network Forensics with Dr. Gail-Joon Ahn: Spring 2015.

· FSE 100 Introduction to Engineering with Dr. Ryan Meuth: Spring 2014.

· CSE 423/424 Capstone I and CSE 485/486 Capstone II with Dr. Debra Calliss: Spring 2014.

· CSE 467 Data & Information Security with Dr. Gail-Joon Ahn: Spring 2011.

SAT/ACT Instructor

Sep 2015 - Oct 2015

Minerva Learning, LLC

Chandler, AZ

Tempe, AZ

· Individual tutor for a high school student preparing for the PSAT.

Teaching Assistant (Instructor of Record)

Aug 2011 - Dec 2014

Arizona State University

Tempe, AZ

· CSE 465 Information Assurance: Fall 2014.

· FSE 100 Introduction to Engineering: Fall 2011 – Fall 2013 (5 semesters).

TEACHING INTERESTS

· Computer and Network Forensics

· Security Toolkit Programming with Python

· Advanced Topics in Digital Forensics

· Cryptography

· Information Assurance

· Software Security

ACADEMIC ACTIVITIES

Fulton Undergraduate Research Initiative (FURI) Mentor

· Adric Rukkila

B.S. in Computer Science at ASU

Sep 2016 - May 2017

Topic: Leveraging Cloud Service APIs for Forensic Data Collection

Undergraduate Honors Thesis Mentor

· Samantha Juntiff

B.S. in Computer Science at ASU

Spring 2015

Thesis: Squeegee: Integrating Forensic Tools for Collaborative Forensic Analysis

SERVICE

Department

· Admin Team: UCSB International Capture the Flag (iCTF)

2017

Publications: [C1]

· Team Leader: ASU team in the UCSB iCTF

2009, 2010, 2014, 2015

· Panelist: PhD Open House Student Panel

Feb 2014, Feb 2015

Profession

· Conference Proceedings Subreviewer:

• ACM CODASPY 2013, 2014, 2015, 2016, 2017

。SACMAT 2014

• ASIACCS 2014

· Student Volunteer:

。ACM CODASPY 2017

。ACM CCS 2014

· Student Program Committee Member:

• IEEE Security & Privacy 2016

Technical Blog Posts

- [BL1] **Mike Mabey**. How eCryptfs Affects Filename Lengths. https://mikemabey.com/blog/2017/08/ecryptfs_filenames.html \(\mathcal{C} \). August 2017.
- [BL2] **Mike Mabey**. How to check out an old version of Chromium OS. https://mikemabey.com/blog/2016/02/check_out_old_chromium.html & February 2016.
- [BL3] **Mike Mabey**. Fixing repo init to check out Chromium OS code. https://mikemabey.com/blog/2015/01/fixing_repo_init_chromium_os.html \(\varphi \). January 2015.
- [BL4] **Mike Mabey**. *Getting into Developer Mode on the HP Pavilion 14 Chromebook*. https://mikemabey.com/blog/2013/05/getting_into_developer_mode.html @. May 2013.
- [BL5] **Mike Mabey**. Debian on Android and my quest for a full-fledged terminal Python IDE. https://mikemabey.com/blog/2012/06/debian_on_android.html @. June 2012.
- [BL6] **Mike Mabey**. *OpenVPN Update: Fixed!* https://mikemabey.com/blog/2012/06/openvpn-update-fixed.html & June 2012.

PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIPS

- · IEEE
 - Cybersecurity Community
 - Internet of Things Community

- · IEEE Computer Society
- · Python Software Foundation (Basic Member) ☑

PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

Preparing Future Faculty (GRD 791 at ASU)
 Aug 2015 – May 2016

 The Preparing Future Faculty (PFF) program is a year-long series of seminars, discussions, and activities designed to expose graduate students and postdocs more fully to the realities of teaching, research, and service in higher education.

REFERENCES

Please feel free to contact any of my references.

Gail-Joon Ahn

Director, Center for Cybersecurity and Digital Forensics ♂

Professor of Computer Science and Engineering

Fulton Entrepreneurial Professor

School of Computing, Informatics and Decision Systems Engineering

Ira A. Fulton Schools of Engineering, Arizona State University

Brickyard Engineering (BYENG) Bldg, Room 486

699 S. Mill Avenue Tempe, AZ 85281

Phone: (480) 965-9007 Fax: (480) 965-2751

http://www.public.asu.edu/~gahn1/&

gahn@asu.edu ♂

Adam Doupé

Associate Director, Center for Cybersecurity and Digital Forensics & Assistant Professor of Computer Science and Engineering

School of Computing, Informatics and Decision Systems Engineering

Ira A. Fulton Schools of Engineering, Arizona State University

Brickyard Engineering (BYENG) Bldg, Room 472

699 S. Mill Avenue

Tempe, AZ 85281 Fax: (480) 965-2751

http://adamdoupe.com

doupe@asu.edu@

Frank J. Grimmelmann

President & CEO/Intelligence Liaison Officer Arizona Cyber Threat Response Alliance (ACTRA)

Phone: (623) 551-1526 Fax: (623) 551-4221

fgrimmelmann@actraaz.org@

Stephen S. Yau

Professor of Computer Science and Engineering

School of Computing, Informatics and Decision Systems Engineering

Ira A. Fulton Schools of Engineering, Arizona State University

Brickyard Engineering (BYENG) Bldg, Room 488

699 S. Mill Avenue Tempe, AZ 85281

Phone: (480) 965-2647

Fax: (480) 965-2751

http://dpse.eas.asu.edu/yau/♂

yau@asu.edu ♂